It isn't a brain supplement, but it's
still going to help prevent you from
developing lifealtering dementia. You
see, dementia is a multiffactorial
disease. And yet, there's one factor
that not only protects you from
dementia, but also protects you from
heart disease. I'm talking about your
blood pressure. Let's discuss the link
between blood pressure and dementia, and
then we'll get into the supplement to
add to your food. So, how does blood
pressure relate to your dementia risk?
Let's find out. In a study of astounding
scale, researchers recruited 34,000
participants over the age of 40 from
across rural villages. All these people
had high blood pressure and were
randomly assigned to usual care or a
more intensive blood pressure lowering
regimen, including blood pressure
medications. Don't worry, smashing
dementia doesn't require drugs. You
won't be sprinkling drugs over your food
unless well that's your style. Not here
to judge. The big picture here is that
one group did not reduce their blood
pressure much and the other reduced
their blood pressure under 130 over 80.
In fact, we can see the data here for
systolic blood pressure. That's the top
number in your blood pressure reading.
The purple are the people on the usual
care without intensive blood pressure
medication and the dashed yellow line is
those in the intervention group. We can
clearly see that there's big difference
in blood pressure over the four years of
the study. The usual care sits around
150 and the intervention group was over
20 points lower around 130 units. Okay,
the setting is set. A big difference in
blood pressure. What happens to
dementia? We can lean on this table.
Don't worry, it's easy to read and we
can focus on just the top here. See the
primary outcome under it is our outcome
of interest. So, dementia. Now comparing
the people in both groups, the risk
ratio is 0.85, which means there's a 15%
reduced risk of dementia between the two
groups. Now, this is an unadjusted
analysis and although this is a
randomized control trial, this is also a
long one, four years. So, the
researchers adjusted for potential
confounding factors like age, sex,
smoking, weight, and more. I'll list
them on the screen. After all those
adjustments, some of which contribute to
dementia risk, a 12% risk reduction
still occurred. That means that the
group that reduce their blood pressure
more had a protection from dementia.
Pretty impressive. Okay, fascinating.
But why does blood pressure relate to
dementia? Well, in fact, it's not as
simple as high blood pressure causes
dementia, as we'll soon see. But
addressing the high blood pressure that
means that the force exerted on your
vasculature the cardiovascular system is
day in day out more extreme than normal
in the brain but also across the body.
This force can damage the cells that
line the blood vessels. Your blood
vessels are primarily defined from a
cellular perspective by a single lining
of endothelial cells that help control
the vascule size as in opening and
tightening of the vascule. Below them
and below a structural section of
proteins is a series of smooth muscle
cells. These cells enact the endothelial
cells bidding. So as force is applied to
the endothelial cells, three things
happen. Probably more, but we'll stick
to these three. One, a primary molecule
that endothelial cells release called
nitric oxide is reduced. This molecule
would normally open the blood vessels,
reducing blood pressure. But constant
high blood pressure causes such
continuous stress that the cells
eventually reduce nitric oxide
generation, exacerbating the problem.
That might also be tied to the constant
pressure applied also leading to an
overwhelming level of damaging molecule
production called reactive oxygen
species causing oxidative stress. This
oxidative stress is characterized by
these ROS or reactive oxygen species
damaging the interior of the endothelial
cell along with damaging the smooth
muscle cells nearby. This can also
reduce nitric oxide production. By the
way, since the brain is filled with
finer blood vessels, it means that the
brain is particularly susceptible.
Finally, these cells also begin
producing more inflammatory molecules
called cytoines that attract immune
cells to the region, increasing the
damage from the activated immune cells.
Well, actually, let me uh quick mention
a last one which I find the most
fascinating. An increase in the
permeability of these endothelial cells.
This matters a lot because your brain is
protected from the rest of your body
through a bloodb brain barrier which
involves the same lining of endothelial
cells as well as a tight wall of brain
cells called aststerytes. The pressure
exerted on these cells causes this tight
tethering between cells creating this
impermeable barrier to loosen. Now
things that might be especially harmful
for the brain can leak through and be
found in the brain where they wouldn't
otherwise be. Think like bacterial
proteins as one example or even immune
cells that are not supposed to be there.
The point being there are many
mechanisms by which blood pressure can
affect the health of the brain like
increasing the risk of dementia. But if
you're thinking the lower the better,
then there's also literature indicating
that low blood pressure may be a risk as
well. The reason is that the perfusion
of the brain, the blood to the brain may
be diminished leading to a lack of
oxygen delivery. I should mention that
there's still more to be explored on
that front. So I'd consider high blood
pressure to have more evidence against
it in relation to dementia. So we've
seen the evidence that blood pressure
affects our dementia risk and we've
discussed in pretty basic terms the
mechanisms of blood pressure on blood
vessel and the brain. Now what can be
done? Let me first point out that if
you're looking for a more in-depth look
on this topic, like uh looking if
smoking habits or age or blood sugar
levels or other factors change this
relationship between blood pressure and
dementia, spoiler, they do. Uh check out
the extended version of this analysis
that you're watching. You can find it in
my Physionic Insiders program along with
access to all my work, my private
podcast, weekly written research
reviews, summaries, actionable
takeaways, a dementia risk calculator,
guides, templates, live sessions with
me, and man oh man, talk about value.
Anyway, to join, just uh click the link
in the description box. I'd really love
to have you there. Here's what you can
do to reduce your dementia risk through
reducing your blood pressure. Well, for
one, exercise of any type reduces blood
pressure, but I've covered uh the most
effective exercises in the past. I'll
link them below for you. Another major
factor is simply dropping body fat,
which is accomplished through nutrition
primarily. Both of these can have a
major role in reducing blood pressure,
but let's assume that you have those in
check and you're looking for an
additional supplement to help you along
the way. The answer is potassium
chloride salt. This is especially
helpful for people who like using salt
in their meals. Substituting with the
potassium chloride salt, say 25% or 50%,
although 25% will be difficult to notice
the difference compared to regular salt.
And yet it will slash your blood
pressure. The reason is due to the
potassium itself having a positive
effect on your kidneys primarily. But be
careful with potassium. It shouldn't be
exclusively consumed. And people with
kidney problems should be especially
careful. So focusing on a blend that's
only 25% potassium chloride helps
prevent issues while reaping the
benefits. It's such a simple switch, yet
it'll help protect you from dementia
through its blood pressure lowering
effects. More on that in just a bit. So
the takeaways here are high blood
pressure, so 140 to 150 over 80 to 90 is
a contributor to dementia and lowering
blood pressure can reduce dementia risk.
Two, you can reduce blood pressure
through any type of exercise as well as
any nutrition that leads to fat loss if
you're overweight. But if you want a
simple supplement that has great
evidence behind its blood pressure
lowering effects, check out a 25%
mixture of potassium chloride salt,
especially as a replacement for your
regular salt to your food. But I mean,
look, don't take my word for it. I cover
the effects of potassium on your blood
pressure through several studies right
here. And like I said, dementia is
multiffactorial. So learn more on the
factors right here. I'll see you over
there. Thanks for hanging out.